Hugues de Laroussilhe

Research Engineer

+33 760575922

huguesdelaroussilhe@gmail.com

SUMMARY

Research engineer with experience in physics, computer science and deep learning. I am enthusiastic about the advancements that machine learning allows in science and engineering. I was involved on several projects applying deep learning solutions to control, enhance or accelerate scientific codes on high-performance computing platforms.

EXPERIENCE

Research Engineer

INRIA/ATOS

This position is part of the joint laboratory between the Atos Ai4Sim R&D team, working on the use of AI for scientific simulations and the INRIA AIRSEA research group, working on the modeling of geophysical flows.

- Run, calibrated and analyzed simulations to generate high fidelity training datasets
- · Developed, tested and benchmarked deep neural network architectures (MLP, CNN and GNN) and training strategies (supervised, unsupervised and reinforcement learning) for processing 3D simulation data
- Designed efficient communication between parallel simulation solvers and ML inference engines
- Contributed to use cases of the methodology applied to fluid dynamics, oceanatmosphere interactions and operational weather forecasts
- Supervised a master student thesis
- Organized and nurtured collaboration between industry and academia through presentations, workshops

PhD Student

University of Zurich - Institute for Computational Science

Supervision: Prof. R. Teyssier (Princeton University) Subgrid models in astrophysical simulations:

- Generated, combined and analyzed large amounts of unstructured 3D simulation data
- Calibrated and compared different turbulence models based on observational data and theoretical constraints
- · Developed analysis tools for data processing and visualization
- Applied computer vision methods (super-resolution, image-to-image translation) to 3D simulation data

Teaching Assistant

Unversity of Zurich

10/2019 - 01/2022 Zurich, Switzerland

Prepared, presented and graded exercises and projects in courses at the University of Zurich

- · Advanced High Performance Computing
- Computational Physics
- · Theoretical Astrophysics

MSc Thesis

ETH Zurich- CSElab

1 01/2019 - 07/2019 Zurich. Switzerland

Supervision: Prof. P. Koumoutsakos (Harvard University) and Dr. G. Novati

Automating turbulence modelling by multi-agent reinforcement learning:

- Trained distributed deep reinforcement learning agents to provide for numerically stable and accurate turbulence models in large eddy simulations
- Publication in Nature Machine Intelligence

LANGUAGES

French

English

SKILLS

Computer Science

Python MPI C++ **Fortran CUDA OpenACC OpenMP** Git CI/CD Docker

Deep Learning

Pytorch Tensorflow 3D Deep Learning

Reinforcement Learning

Generative Models

Science

Simulations Physics Fluid Dynamics

Mathematics Statistics

EDUCATION

MSc in Physics

Ecole Normale Supérieure de Lyon

2017 - 2019

· Theoretical Physics

BSc in Physics

Université Grenoble Alpes

2016 - 2017

· Physics - Computer Science

BSc in Engineering

Institut National Polytechnique PHELMA

2013 - 2016

Physics - Electronics - Material Science - Computer Science